Koustav Ghosal

Bio

I am a Research Assistant at the V-SENSE lab in Trinity College Dublin. My current research is focused on developing applications for 3D human pose estimation and 3D mesh sequence compression using graph neural networks and vision transformers. I hold a PhD and a research masters in Computer Vision.

I am passionate about problems in computer vision and natural language processing. Specifically, I am interested in multitask learning, generative adversarial learning, semi and unsupervised learning.

Education

PhD in Computer Science

Trinity College Dublin, Ireland. 2021

Topic: Applications in Image Aesthetics Using Deep Learning

Supervisor: Prof. Aljosa Smolic

Masters (Research) in Computer Science

IIIT Hyderabad, India. 2016

Topic: A Sketch-based Approach for Multimedia Retrieval

Supervisor: Prof. Anoop Namboodiri

Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science & Engineering

WBUT, India. 2011

Experiences

Research Assistant | V-SENSE, Dublin | March 2021 - Present

- Applying deep learning for developing applications in creative technologies, supervised by Prof. Aljosa Smolic.
- $\bullet\,$ Developing weakly supervised applications for image aesthetics assessment using noisy web data.
- Exploring vision transformers and graph neural networks for 3D human pose estimation in rugby videos.
- Working on 3D mesh sequence compression using graph and 3D convolutional networks for applications in augmented and mixed reality.

Machine Learning Intern | IRISA, France | June - September, 2016

- Worked on detecting and tracking tidal channels at Mont Saint-Michel Bay with the OBELIX team under the supervision of Prof. Sébastien Lefèvre.
- Developed an annotation tool and proposed segmentation algorithms using CNNs for multi-spectral data using Keras.

Machine Learning Consultant | Deep Learn Labs, India | August, 2015 - March, 2016

- Implemented deep learning based solution for vehicle detection and classification using OpenCV, Caffe and C++ towards the proof of concept.
- Developed an intelligent annotation tool using Python and QT for quickly labelling a large collection traffic videos.

Android App Developer | OMitra, India | August 2014 - January 2015

• Developed live in-journey features for the proof of concept such as chats, meal and cab bookings (Android utility app for train journeys)

Natural Language Processing Intern | IIT, Kharagpur | April - July, 2012

- Curated a large text corpus in Bengali language for studying readability of Bengali documents.
- Developed a tool using Python and QT for analyzing documents and predict standard readability scores such as Flesch, SMOG etc.

Skills

Subject Areas: Computer Vision, Image Processing, Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Graph Neural Networks, Convolutional Neural Networks, Generative Adversarial Learning, Semi and Unsupervised Learning, Transformers

Coding: C, C++, Java, Android, Python, Matlab

Libraries and Tools: PyTorch, PyTorch Geometric, Tensorflow, Caffe, SciPy, NLTK, GitHub, Docker

Publications

- 1. Koustav Ghosal, Aljosa Smolic. Image Aesthetics Assessment Using Graph Attention Network, IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (2021) (under review)
- 2. Ojasvi Yadav, Koustav Ghosal, Sebastian Lutz, and Aljosa Smolic. Frequency-domain loss function for deep exposure correction of dark images. Signal, Image and Video Processing (2021).
- 3. Koustav Ghosal, Aakanksha Rana, and Aljosa Smolic. Aesthetic Image Captioning From Weakly-Labelled Photographs., Workshop In Cross-Modal Learning in Real World, International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) 2019, Seoul
- 4. Xu Zheng, Tejo Chalasani, Koustav Ghosal, Sebastian Lutz, Aljosa Smolic. STaDA: Style Transfer as Data Augmentation., 14th International Conference on Computer Vision Theory and Applications, VISAPP 2019, Prague
- 5. Koustav Ghosal, Mukta Prasad, Aljosa Smolic, A Geometry-Sensitive Approach for Photographic Style Classification, Irish Machine Vision and Image Processing Conference, August 2018 (IMVIP), Belfast.
- 6. Koustav Ghosal, Ameya Prabhu, Riddhiman Dasgupta, Anoop M. Namboodiri, *Learning Clustered Subspaces for sketch-based Image Retrieval*, Asian Conference on Pattern Recognition (ACPR), November 2015, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.
- 7. Koustav Ghosal, Anoop M. Namboodiri, A Sketch-Based Approach to Video Retrieval using Qualitative Features, Proceedings of the Ninth Indian Conference on Computer Vision, Graphics and Image Processing (ICVGIP), 14-17 Dec 2014, Bangalore, India.
- 8. Sanchit Aggarawal, Koustav Ghosal, Pulkit Singhal, Priyanka Srivastava, Effect of Learning on Audio Spatial Working Memory, Spatial Cognition 2014, Bremen, Germany, 15-19 September 2014.

Teaching & Supervision

Teaching (Demonstrator):

- 1. Microprocessor Systems, Trinity College, Dublin. (January April, 2020)
- 2. Advanced Computer Vision, Trinity College, Dublin. (September December, 2018 & 2019)
- 3. Computer Vision, Trinity College, Dublin. (September December, 2017 & 2019)
- 4. Statistical Methods in AI, IIIT Hyderabad. (Monsoon, 2014)
- 5. Cognitive Neuroscience, IIIT Hyderabad. (Spring 2014)

Thesis Supervision:

- 1. Data augmentation with Artistic Style, Xu Zheng (MSc)
- $2.\ \ Understanding\ the\ Geometry\ of\ Photographic\ Images\ Using\ Deep\ Learning,\ Sarvani\ Chakrabarty\ (MSc)$
- 3. Style Transfer for 360 images, Xin Zhang (MSc)
- 4. Improving Low Light Photography with Generative Adversarial Networks, Ojasvi Yadav (UG)